Guide to the Lefferts Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lefferts family papers
1712-1936
MS 319
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
(1 box, 1 folio)
Financial papers, deeds, legal documents, bills and receipts and other papers relating to the Lefferts and related families of New York. The papers include a group of documents concerning Aaron Burr's efforts in 1833-1834 to obtain a government pension. The papers also contain newspaper clippings covering the period 1830-1936.
Lefferts family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Mario Pagano and Mrs. John Peter Beck, 1955.
Scope and Contents
Financial and real estate papers, legal documents, correspondence, and other papers relating to the Lefferts family of New York City and vicinity, and dating from 1712 to 1850, make up this collection. Various descendants of Jacob Lefferts (1686-1768), fourth son of Leffert Pietersen van Haughwout, a Huguenot immigrant from North Holland to New York in 1660, are represented. For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Lefferts family, please consult the Genealogical Chart. Further details can be found in Genealogy of the Lefferts Family, 1650-1878, by Teunis G. Bergen, 1878.
Also included in the papers are a group of documents concerning Aaron Burr's efforts to obtain a government pension in 1833-1834 for his Revolutionary War services. While most of the documents are in the hand of his clerk or of people making depositions, a few are signed by Burr.
The contents of the collection have been arranged chronologically and a brief description of each item provided. Most of the papers are in very fragile condition and require careful handling.
The papers were the gift of Mrs. Mario Pagano and Mrs. John Peter Beck in 1955.
Biographical / Historical
Various descendants of Jacob Lefferts (1686-1768), a fourth son of Leffert Pietersen van Haughwout, a Huguenot immigrant from North Holland to New York in 1660, are represented.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Lefferts family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Families; Military pensions -- United States -- Revolution, 1775-1783; New York (State); United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Deeds; Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836; Lefferts family
- Inventory, 1712-1850, 1930-1936, undated
  - Lott, Abraham: transfer of land in King's County to Marten Adriaense (in Dutch), 1712 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Remsen, Rem: bond to Jeremiah Remsen, 1728 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Van der Beek, Rem: bond with Christofell Van der Beek to Ida Van Wickelen, 1732 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rapelye, Jannetie (Lefferts): receipt to executors of her husband Jeronemus Rapely's estate, [1754?] May 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Raypelye, Jannetie (Lefferts): receipt to executors of her husband Jeronemus Rapely's estate for money to maintain her son Jeronemus Rapelye, 1758 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rapelye, Jeronemus estate: receipts from various persons to Rem Remsen and Nicholaes Veghate, executors, 1762-1769 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lefferts, Barent: pocket account book, mostly bland, 1763, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Berdeau, Peter: bill of sale for a slave to Barent Lefferts, 1766 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Andriese, Andries: bond to Gerret Middach, 1768 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lefferts, Barent: bond to Gerrit Noorstrant, 1772 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wyckoff, Femmetie (Mrs. Cornelius): receipt to Hendrick Eldert, Nicholas Wyckoff and Rem Remsen, executors, for a legacy under the will of Hendrick Wyckoff, 1773 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conditions of sale of a plantation, Bedford, King's County, 1774 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bloom, Jacob: order on Barent Lefferts in favor of Barent Andriese, 1775 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elder, J.: ALS to Mr. Lefferts, Charlestown, [Mass.], 1781 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gerritsen, Samuel W.: Als to Barent Lefferts, 1783 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miller, Josiah: receipt to Barent Lefferts, 1784 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Remsen, Captain: order to freeholders of Brooklyn to supply their quota of wood, 1785 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lefferts, Barent: Promissory note to Jacob van der Bilt, 1787 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Simons, Andrew: quit claim to Gerrit Wyckoff, Jacob Bloom, and Barent Lefferts, executors of the estate of Andress Andressen, 1791 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New York (State), tax collector: receipt for carriage tax to Barent Lefferts, 1802 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lefferts, Rem: sundry farm and stock-raising accounts, 1809-1814, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Washington Insurance Co., New York: insurance policy to Abigail Fowler, 1816 March 16 (Box 2)
    General
    See: Folio 2
  - Spader, William: bond to executors of the estate of Michal Vandervoort, 1816 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ryerson, Jacob, Jr.: agreement with Rem and Maria Lefferts for maintenance of a fence, 1825 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Remsen, Jacob: two bonds to Johannes Remsen, 1825 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lefferts, Rem: "An account of the blacks work and monies" received from R. Lefferts, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Washington Insurance Co., New York: insurance policy to George L. Cornell, 1828 October 14 (Box 2)
  - Lefferts, Rem: lease agreement with Abraham Brown for land between Bedford and Flatubush, 1829 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lefferts, Rem: lease agreement with Peter C. Bell for house and land in Brooklyn, 1833 December 23 (Box 2)
  - Edsall, Daniel: agreement as apprentice to John Degraw to learn house carpentry, 1833 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Burr, Aaron: papers dealing with Burr's efforts to secure a pension, 1833-1834 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Cuppin, S.: ALS to Nelson Chase, Worcester, 1834 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lefferts, Rem: lease agreement with Charles Basham for house and land in Bedford, 1834 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Warmington, William: certificate with Louis Dufland to the condition of a mare sold to Mr. Lefferts, 1835 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Halsey, Frederick: receipt to Rem Lefferts, 1835 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Incomplete deed for land in Brooklyn to Rem and Maria Lefferts, 1835 (Box 2)
  - Lefferts, Rem deed to Cornelius W. Van Brunt for land in Flatbush, King's County, 1836 September 1 (Box 2)
  - Burtis, Stilwell & Co.: bill to Rem Lefferts, 1836 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lefferts, Rem: lease agreement with William L. Haskins for house and land in Brooklyn, 1838 August 1 (Box 2)
  - Whitson, Silas: receipt to Rem Lefferts in a horse trade, 1838 November (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Contribution Fire Insurance Co.: certificate of policy to Abraham and Henry Brown, 1838 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lefferts Rem: bond to David Carll, 1839 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Baisley, John: receipt to Mr. Sexton, 1841 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brooklyn Horse Guards: printed invitation to annual ball, 1841 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Murphy, John G.: deed to Rem Lefferts for land in Brooklyn, 1842 March 7 (Box 2)
  - Lefferts, Rem: bond to Rufus R. Skeel, 1842 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lefferts, Rem: lease agreement with James Powell, 1844 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Skeel, Rufus R.: assignment to Philip Dater, guardian of the infant children of Theron and Eliza Skeel, of a mortgage against Rem and Maria Lefferts, 1844 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Disbrow, S.M.: ALS to his uncle Rem Lefferts, Sr., 1845 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rapelye, George: declaration with John Purdy of errors in description of property to be released to Rem Lefferts, 1846 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Olcott, McKesson & Co.: bill to Rem Lefferts, 1846 December (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sloane, William: bill for a rug to R. Lefferts, 1850 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Troy House: bill to Mr. Lefferts, 1850 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Long Island Bank: notice to Rem Lefferts of note due, [n.y.] January 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lefferts, Rem: itinerary New York to Albany with L. Lefferts, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1930-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)